Okay, בוקר טוב. boker tov. All right, so today's דף daf is
יד, yud dalet, and we pick up towards the bottom of יג
עמוד ב. yud gimmel amud bet. We're dealing with the debate in
the משנה mishna between רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel and רבי יהושע Rabbi
Yehoshua about whether when there's a question about a woman who went
in private with a man or slept with a man, what the
man's status was, whether it affects the woman's status, and if the
woman became pregnant, what the fetus's status was.
So the גמרא Gemara now picks up with the following.
אמר רבי יוחנן. Amar Rabbi Yochanan. So it is about 20 lines
from the bottom, line starts with the word פוסל. posel. Okay. So
the גמרא Gemara says like this, אמר רבי יוחנן. Amar Rabbi Yochanan.
So and what we've also established is that רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua
who's strict is strict even in a case of when they're in
private, even not in a case when you know that the woman
has had sex. So even in just the case where they've been
in seclusion, he's strict. So אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, says
רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, לדברי המכשיר בה
מכשיר בביתה. le-divrei ha-machshir bah machshir be-vittah. The one who says that
her status is fine, the fetus's status is also fine. ולדברי הפוסל
בה פוסל בביתה. u-le-divrei ha-posel bah posel be-vittah. If her status is
not good then the fetus's status is not good. The bigger חידוש
chiddush was the first part of the statement, that she has a
חזקת כשרות, chezkat kashrut, you know that her status began as okay,
so there's more of an inclination to say that you're not going
to invalidate her out of doubt. But the fetus, you never knew
its status. And nevertheless says רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan according to רבן
גמליאל Rabban Gamliel who believes her status vis-à-vis her, he will also
believe it vis-à-vis the fetus.
And it says the daughter, because most likely if she had sex
with a man she wasn't allowed to, the daughter would become invalid
to a כהן. kohen. Okay. רבי אלעזר
אומר לדברי המכשיר בה פוסל בביתה. Rabbi Elazar omer le-divrei ha-machshir bah
posel be-vittah. No. Even רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel who says she's okay
would say that her daughter that resulted from this sex with this
man would be invalid. We'd have to suspect that she'd be a
חללה chalala or some other type of invalidity for a כהן. kohen.
אמר רבא, Amar Rava, said רבא, Rava, מאי טעמא דרבי אלעזר, mai
ta'ama de-Rabbi Elazar, what's the reason of רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar that
makes a difference between her and the daughter? בשלמא היא אית לה
חזקה דכשרות, Bishlama hi it lah chezakah de-kashrut, I understand she has
a חזקה דכשרות chezakah de-kashrut being kosher until she had
this meeting with this man. ביתה לית לה חזקה דכשרות, Bittah leit
lah chezakah de-kashrut, but the fetus, the child, we never knew its
status and it might have been conceived in sin and therefore the
fetus because of the doubt would be invalid. So this is the
question whether רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel who says that she's okay would
say the child is okay as well. איתיביה, Eitivei, asked on this,
איתיביה רבי אלעזר לרבי יוחנן, eitivei Rabbi Elazar le-Rabbi Yochanan, רבי אלעזר
Rabbi Elazar challenged רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan who
was the one who said that the fetus is also okay. במה
דברים אמורים בעדות אשה בגופה, Bameh devarim amurim be-edut ishah be-gufah, the
ברייתא beraita we quoted yesterday said when is it true that she's
believed when it comes to her about her own person? אבל עדות
אשה בביתה, Aval edut ishah be-vittah, when it comes to her about
her daughter, דברי הכל הולד שתוקי, divrei ha-kol ha-valad shetuki,
everybody would agree that the child is a שתוקי. shetuki. שתוקי Shetuki
from the word שתק, shetok, silence, which means you silence somebody who
asks about, you know, if the child says who's my father you
say shut up, you say be quiet, which means that there's a
doubt about the parentage. And presumably, now of course there's a doubt,
we don't know who the father is or we don't know for
sure, but שתוקי shetuki normally means that that's a particular status of
invalidity because you don't know there's a potential invalidity here and she
wouldn't be able to marry a כהן. kohen. So the ברייתא beraita
was pretty clear that even according to רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel the
child has a problematic status. מאי לאו שתוקי ופסול, Mai lav shetuki
u-pasul, does it not mean a שתוקי shetuki and therefore invalid to
marry a כהן? kohen? לא, Lo, says רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan back.
שתוקי וכשר, Shetuki ve-kasher, it's true you don't know who the father
is, but the child's status is not problematic, she can still marry
a כהן. kohen. So the גמרא Gemara says, ומי איכא שתוקי כשר?
u-mi ika shetuki kasher? Is there anybody who would be called a
שתוקי shetuki and still be כשר? kasher? The whole point of שתוקי
shetuki is to say that it's a problematic status. אין, In, yes,
כשמואל, ke-Shmuel, like שמואל. Shmuel. דאמר שמואל, De-amar Shmuel, עשרה כהנים עומדים,
asara kohanim omdim, there are ten כהנים kohanim standing in a group,
ופירש אחד מהם ובעל, u-peirash echad me-hem u-va'al, and one of them
left and had sex with a woman and came back to the
group. Okay. So then and you have no idea who the כהן,
kohen, I mean presumably, you know, at least the man and the
woman, well at least the man knows who, anyway, but we don't
have any idea who the father was, but you know it's a
כהן. kohen. Okay.
So והולד שתוקי, ve-ha-valad shetuki, the child is a שתוקי. shetuki. Now
why is it a שתוקי? shetuki? You know the mother didn't have
sex with somebody that was invalid, again it was a single woman,
so the child is totally כשר, kasher,
regardless, I mean okay you don't know the father is, but its
status is totally כשר. kasher. So the גמרא Gemara says,
מאי שתוקי, mai shetuki, what does שתוקי shetuki mean? אילימא שמשתקין אותו
מנכסי אביו, Ilima she-meshattikin oto mi-nichsei aviv, if it means שתוקי shetuki
that you silence him from the father's inheritance, meaning if one of
the כהנים kohanim dies the child isn't entitled to inherit because you
don't know who the father is. So the גמרא Gemara says, that's
obvious. פשיטא. Pshita. ומי ידעינן אבוה מנו? U-mi yad'inan avuha manu? We
don't know who the father is. You don't have to tell me
that he doesn't inherit when one of these כהנים kohanim dies. die,
you don't know who the father is, so of course he's not
going to be able to get a portion in the estate.
So by the way, you know, if a child is a ממזר
mamzer as opposed to like secular law, which is a bastard child
does not inherit the father, you know in הלכה Halacha a child
who is a ממזר mamzer does inherit the father even... so but
that's when you know who the father is. Okay, but here the
point is you don't know the father is, so of course there's
nothing to inherit. So that can't be what שתוקי shtuki means. So
ומי ידעינן אבוה מנו? umi yadainan avuh manu? אלא שמשתיקין אותו מדין
כהונה. ela shemashtikin oto midin kehuna. So the שתוקי shtuki here that
has an implication in terms of personal status is not that he
can't marry like a כהן kohen or, you know, or she can't
marry a כהן, kohen, that somehow it's a real personal status issue
in terms of, you know, marriage and so on and doubtful פסול.
pasul. That's not true because you know that the father is כשר
kasher and therefore you know the child is כשר. kasher. So the
only שתוקי shtuki that would be relevant here would be that he
cannot serve as a כהן, kohen, even though you know the father
is כשר, kasher, since you don't know who the father is. דכתיב,
dechtiv, as the verse says: והיתה לו ולזרעו אחריו ברית כהונת עולם.
vehayta lo ulezaro acharav brit kehunat olam. It shall be for him
the כהונה kehuna and for his seed afterwards an everlasting covenant of
כהונה. kehuna. מי שזרעו מיוחס אחריו, mi shezaro meyuchas acharav,
somebody who knows whose child is attributed to him is like, you
know, you know the יחוס, yichus, you know the relationship. יצא זה
שאין זרעו מיוחס אחריו, yatza zeh she'ein zaro meyuchas acharav, and in
this case where you don't know, the guy doesn't know who his
father is, therefore he cannot serve as a כהן. kohen. So even
if he knows he's a כהן, kohen, if he doesn't know who
his father is, he cannot serve as such. So therefore, when it
says that the child is a שתוקי, shtuki, we're going to interpret
it very narrowly to mean a שתוקי shtuki so that he will,
if he's a כהן, kohen, he won't be able to serve as
a כהן. kohen. But רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is going to insist
that the child will not have a problematic in terms of other
aspects of personal status. So if the child is a girl, she
will be able to marry a כהן. kohen. So very important debate.
On the one extreme you have רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua that says
even if we don't know she had sex, she just went in
private, she's invalid and certainly the child would be invalid because she
might have had sex with, I don't know, a ממזר mamzer or
a חלל chalal or something that would invalidate her status vis-a-vis a
כהן. kohen. So she's invalid and the child is invalid. And as
we saw yesterday, even if it's most of the men that she
might have had sex with, you know, are ones which would have
not invalidated her status. She's a single woman, she's in a city
that's like all Jews, and it's only a tiny percentage. רבי יהושע
Rabbi Yehoshua is very מחמיר. machmir. And once she's in private and
seclusion with a man, that's it, her status, child status, whole thing
is in question. רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel goes the opposite extreme. Even
if we know she's had sex, her status is okay, even if
it's out in the field where most people are non-Jews and therefore
most acts of sex could invalidate her. We're going to say it's
okay, again, a big חידוש, chiddush, because we're going to trust what
she says. And not only that, but according to רבי יוחנן, Rabbi
Yochanan, not only is her status okay but the status of the
fetus is also okay, at least according to רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan.
Okay, so a very wide range. Of course there רבי אלעזר Rabbi
Elazar would say no, even רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel would admit the
fetus is a problem, but רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says the fetus
is okay. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara has a case.
Last line of יג עמוד ב. yud gimmel amud bet. ההוא ארוס
וארוסתו, hahu arus ve'arusato,
a certain betrothed man and woman. Okay, so they're not supposed to
be having sex yet, but as we know in יהודה Yehuda they
would, and obviously presumably sometimes they would anyway even though they're not
supposed to be. So you have a betrothed man and
woman דאתו לקמיה דרב יוסף, da'atu lekamei deRav Yosef, they came in
front of רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, and she was pregnant. היא אמרה
מיניה הוא, hi amra minei hu, she said: yes, I'm pregnant because
it's from him. You know, yes, we're not yet נשואין, nisuin, but
we've been sleeping together. והוא אומר, vehu omer, and he says, אין
מינאי, in minai, yes, it's my child. Okay, so everybody agrees whose
child it is. Nevertheless, you know, we're like oh, here's a married
woman, you know, here's a woman who's not yet supposed to be
having sex with her husband, she got pregnant, I wonder who the
father is? But they're both saying that he's the father. So אמר
רב יוסף, amar Rav Yosef, top of יד עמוד א, yud dalet
amud aleph, says רב יוסף: Rav Yosef: למה למיחש לה, lemai lemichash
lah, what should we be concerned about?
חדא
דהא קמודה, chada deha kamodeh, number one, that they both agree, or
he agrees more significantly, that it's his child. ועוד, ve'od, and number
two, האמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל הלכה כרבן גמליאל, ha'amar Rav Yehuda
amar Shmuel halacha keRabban Gamliel,
we rule like רבן גמליאל. Rabban Gamliel. So we rule like רבן
גמליאל Rabban Gamliel that even if he wouldn't agree, if she says
that the father was somebody who's כשר, kasher, then it's not a
problem. So אמר ליה אביי, amar lei Abaye, so okay, great, we'll
believe them. אמר ליה אביי, amar lei Abaye, Abaye said: one minute,
ובהא כי לא מודה משמיה דרבן גמליאל, uvha ki lo modeh mashmia
deRabban Gamliel, are you suggesting that had the father, had the husband
not admitted that it was his child, רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel would
say that this case is okay? והאמר ליה שמואל לרב יהודה שיננא
שרפונא הלכה כרבן גמליאל, veha'amar lei Shmuel leRav Yehuda shinena sharpona halacha
keRabban Gamliel, but שמואל Shmuel said to רב יהודה: Rav Yehuda: שיננא,
shinena, שרפונא, sharpona, it's true we rule like רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel
that the woman is okay, maybe even the child, but nevertheless ואת
לא תעביד עובדא עד דאיכא רוב כשרים, ve'at lo ta'avid uvda ad
de'ika rov kisherim,
don't actually in practice rule like רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel unless the
majority of the people were... that he might have had sex with
are כשר, kasher, would not invalidate her status, okay? So it's true
that רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel says, as I said a minute ago,
that we would say her status is okay, even if we knew
she had sex, even if most of the people around would be
invalid for, you know, would invalidate her status. But here רב יהודה,
Rav Yehuda,
one minute, but here what is it? שמואל Shmuel said to רב
יהודה Rav Yehuda that even though that's true, right, a minute ago
we said אמר רב יהודה שמואל הלכה כרבן גמליאל Amar Rav Yehuda
Shmuel halacha k'Rabban Gamliel that רב יהודה Rav Yehuda said in the
name of שמואל Shmuel we rule like this, שמואל Shmuel said back
to רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, even though we rule like this, in
practice, in set and theory, in practice don't act on it unless
most of the people around would have not invalidated her status, are
כשרי. ksheiri. And what's the story here? Well here, if she's a
married woman, every single other man other than her husband would have
invalidated her status, right? You get that? As opposed to case of
a single woman. A single woman the only person that would invalidate
her status for a כהן Kohen would be a non-Jew or somebody
like let's say a חלל chalal or a ממזר. mamzer. It'd be
very small number of people, right? I mean non-Jew if she's in
a Jewish town. But if she's a married woman, everybody would have
invalidated her status except for her husband. So here we're saying we
might rule like רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel but don't act on it
when most people would invalidate her. Well, that's the case here. So
the גמרא Gemara says והכא רוב פסולים אצלה. v'hakha rov psulim etzla.
So how can we be saying that oh, well, even if the
A, the husband admitted, B, even if he didn't admit, we rule
like רבן גמליאל. Rabban Gamliel. We wouldn't rule like רבן גמליאל Rabban
Gamliel in a case like this because most people would have invalidated
her. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute, ולטעמיך תיפשוט לך הגופא.
u-letamayikh tifsot lakh ha-gufa.
One minute, before we ask that, let's ask let's deal with that
statement itself. Like we should be bothered by the statement itself. הלכה
ולא תעביד עובדא. halacha v'lo tavid uvda.
So what does it mean? We rule like רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel
but don't act on it. Don't actually פסקן pasken it. Unless most
people are כשר. kasher. So how could you say both? If we
rule like it, we should פסקן pasken like it. Which is a
funny question because very often the גמרא Gemara sort of has a
position in theory but not in practice. But anyway, let's see what
the גמרא Gemara does with it. For what purpose are we saying
the הלכה halacha is like him if we're saying you shouldn't פסקן
pasken it when most people are פסול. pasul. Thank you. אלא מאי
אית לך למימר הלכה לכתחילה הא דיעבד ella mai ith lakh lemeimar
halacha lekhatkhila ha dieved that when we say we rule, excuse me,
don't, excuse me,
okay, about to sneeze, right,
it
passed. When we say don't rule like him in practice, we mean
לכתחילה. lekhatkhila. לכתחילה lekhatkhila don't rule like רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel unless
most people are כשר. kasher. However, when we say that the הלכה
halacha is like רבן גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel, what we mean is בדיעבד,
bedieved, if it already occurred. So what would be the difference of
לכתחילה lekhatkhila בדיעבד? bedieved? Not לכתחילה lekhatkhila בדיעבד bedieved since she sleep
with the man, she already slept with the man and she was
in private. But there's a לכתחילה lekhatkhila בדיעבד bedieved in the following.
She comes to say, right, can I marry a כהן? Kohen? So
what we would say is, look, in theory we פסקן pasken like
רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel and since most are כשר, kasher, we, I
mean even if most are פסול, pasul, we should believe you and
we should allow you to marry the כהן. Kohen. But given that
most were פסול, pasul, we're not going to לכתחילה lekhatkhila let you
marry a כהן. Kohen. Then she goes ahead and she ignores us,
or she never asked us, and she married a כהן. Kohen. Are
we going to say they have to get a divorce? So once
it's already a בדיעבד bedieved case, we're going to say, all right,
it's already בדיעבד, bedieved, in that scenario we'll rule like רבן גמליאל
Rabban Gamliel even though most are פסול pasul and we'll say that
your status is still okay. All right, so that's number one, right?
Is this clear now everybody? Meaning we had a whole discussion yesterday,
how do we rule? Here we're saying
we rule
like
רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel even if most are פסול, pasul, רוב פסולים
אצלה. rov psulim etzla. And the גמרא Gemara says we rule that
way, but we rule that way only בדיעבד. bedieved. לכתחילה lekhatkhila we
would say that if most of the people are פסול, pasul, right,
by this single woman which basically means let's say a non-Jewish town
would be a common scenario, we won't לכתחילה lekhatkhila let her marry
a כהן. Kohen. But בדיעבד, bedieved, if she did marry a כהן,
Kohen, we'll let her stay married. If most people are כשר, kasher,
like it's a Jewish town, then we'll say even לכתחילה lekhatkhila she's
claiming the father was not was was כשר, kasher, we
then even לכתחילה lekhatkhila we'll believe her and let her marry a
כהן. Kohen. So we rule so again, we don't know who the
father was, she claims he was כשר. kasher. According to we rule
like רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel even if most are פסול. pasul. But
that's בדיעבד bedieved once she got married. לכתחילה lekhatkhila we're going to
insist before to allow her to get married that most are כשר.
kasher. This case in the גמרא Gemara where it was a betrothed
man and woman and they both said that it was the husband’s
child, so number one he said we believe them because they both
admit whose child it was. But number two even if they wouldn't
both admit, even if the man would say, no it's not my
child, I haven't slept with her, and she said it was his
child, which is pretty amazing because here we actually would have a
case of let's say contradictory testimony. Or let's say he would say,
I don't know, let's say a better case, he would say, I
don't know, yes we've been sleeping around before the חופה Chuppah since
the אירוסין, Erusin, but who knows? Maybe she slept with another man
as well. I can't tell you that it's my child. That's going
to be a great marriage going forward anyway. In that type of
a case, right, so רוב פסולין אצלה Rov Psulin Etzlah because anybody
other than this guy would invalidate her status. Okay? So, but it's
also a בדיעבד Bediavad case, because if we were to say, well,
we have to question who the father is and who she slept
with, then we would insist that the husband divorce her, because we're
saying it might have been another man. So since that's a בדיעבד
Bediavad case, we will rule there like רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel even
in a case of רוב פסולין Rov Psulin because it is a
case of בדיעבד. Bediavad.
So these days, if a person is getting more פרום Frum and
wants to marry a כהן, Kohen, you know, they may have not
been...
All right, so that's a general question about a person, a woman's
past sexual history marrying a כהן. Kohen. I'm not going to get
into that right now. Okay? That's obviously stuff that'll come up more
when we do קידושין. Kiddushin. Yes? Yes? Okay fine. So, so okay,
השתא בדיעבד. Hashta Bediavad. So רמי ליה אביי לרבא. Rami Leh Abbaye
LeRava. So אביי Abbaye asked רבא: Rava: ומי אמר רבי יהושע איננה
נאמנת? Umi Amar Rabbi Yehoshua Einena Ne'emenes?
So that was an important application of how do we פוסקין. Poskin.
Do we פוסקין Poskin like רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel לכתחילה Lechatchila when
רוב כשר, Rov Kasher, בדיעבד Bediavad even if רוב פסול? Rov Psul?
We have not spelled out how we פוסקין Poskin about the status
of the child. That's a debate of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan וריש
לקיש. VeReish Lakish. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this: רמי
ליה אביי לרבא, Rami Leh Abbaye LeRava, or לרבה. LeRaba. ומי
אמר רבי יהושע איננה נאמנת? Umi Amar Rabbi Yehoshua Einena Ne'emenes? Is
it true that רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua really says that a woman
isn't believed when she says who the man is that she slept
with? ורמינהו, Veraminehu, I'll ask you on this. A משנה Mishnah in
עדיות, Eduyos, העיד Heid where the positions of רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua
and רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel seem to get reversed. העיד רבי יהושע
ורבי יהודה בן בתירה, Heid Rabbi Yehoshua VeRabbi Yehuda Ben Beseira, רבי
יהושע ורבי יהודה בן בתירה Rabbi Yehoshua VeRabbi Yehuda Ben Beseira testified,
על אלמנת עיסה, Al Almanat Issa, a widow of dough. Now dough
here means, the image of dough is that you put a lot
of things into the dough, I mean not a lot, but okay,
you put water and flour and maybe yeast and salt. So it's
a mixture. So that means that there's some like, you know, mixed
lineage. There's some question about who the parents are, some question of
it's not a question of like a pedigreed lineage, right? You know,
there's a mixed lineage and therefore the status is questionable. So what
is the story of an אלמנת עיסה? Almanat Issa? So we're going
to say that the story is is that there was a case
of a ספק חלל. Safek Challal. Here's the scenario that רש"י Rashi
spells out. Okay? A woman is divorced from her husband,
but we don't know she was definitely divorced. A classic case is
the guy threw a גט Get but it wasn't clear whether the
גט Get got within her like range or not within her range,
okay? So she got a גט Get but it was a question
whether it took effect. And then a day after he gave her
this ספק גט, Safek Get, he died. So this woman is a
ספק אלמנה, Safek Almana, ספק גרושה. Safek Gerusha. Then she goes ahead
and she marries a כהן. Kohen. Okay? So if she is a
גרושה, Gerusha, then by marrying a כהן Kohen she becomes a חללה,
Challalah, right, because she's a גרושה Gerusha having sex with a כהן,
Kohen, she the woman becomes a חללה Challalah and the child becomes
a חלל. Challal. Okay? So she went ahead, she had sex with
a כהן, Kohen, so now she's a ספק חללה Safek Challalah and
the child is a ספק חלל. Safek Challal. Everybody with me still?
This child, this boy that she had, then marries a woman. So
now now this ספק חלל Safek Challal man is having sex with
a woman, so she by extension becomes a ספק חללה Safek Challalah
and then he dies. So that's an אלמנת עיסה. Almanat Issa. Okay,
she's an אלמנה Almana from this man and she might be a
חללה Challalah based on some doubt. Now רש"י Rashi by the way,
that's only one ספק. Safek. The גמרא Gemara later, just to anticipate,
is going to call it a ספק ספיקא. Sfeik Sfeika. So what's
the ספק ספיקא? Sfeik Sfeika? So one explanation רש"י Rashi says it's
not really a ספק ספיקא, Sfeik Sfeika, it's just a ספק Safek
that traveled two generations, right? So first you didn't know the story
about the mother, and then you didn't know the story about the
child, and then you didn't know the story about like the child's
wife, right, the boy's wife. Because if the mother was a חללה,
Challalah, then the child was a חלל, Challal, then then then the
child's wife was a חללה. Challalah. So right, so it's not really
a ספק ספיקא, Sfeik Sfeika, it's a ספק Safek that traveled two
generations. But then רש"י Rashi gives a scenario of a ספק ספיקא.
Sfeik Sfeika. In addition to the one ספק Safek we just said,
he said, and let's say the woman who got the ספק גט
Safek Get and then her husband died, and then the man died,
so ספק גרושה, Safek Gerusha, ספק אלמנה, Safek Almana, she let's say
she married another man within three months of the death of of
the first guy and she became pregnant right right at and, you
know, she had a baby like, you know, I don't know, seven
months after. So then you don't know, is the child the child
from the second union and therefore a ספק חלל, Safek Challal, right,
because of what we just said, or a child from the first
union and therefore not a ספק Safek because it was from the
husband that just died, right? Then she it was conceived... Even before
the whole גט *get* and everything took place. So it could be
a ספק safek ספיקא *sfek sfeka*. He would only be a חלל
chalal, *chalal* if number one the second guy was his father, right,
and number two that the mother was a גרושה grusha *grusha* not
an אלמנה Almana, *almana*. Okay, so that's this אמנת אישה *Amanat Isha*,
all right, so that's the story. We got this woman who might
be a חללה *chalala*, might be a ספק Safek ספיקא חללה *sfek
sfeka chalala*, that's the story. Okay, so they testified about this אמנת
אישה *Amanat Isha* שהיא כשירה לכהונה *shehi kshira l'kehuna* that can go
ahead and marry a כהן kohen. *kohen*. So you see why do
you say it's okay? רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua. *Rabbi Yehoshua* says when
there's a question who she slept with and even if she said
"I am telling you the guy I slept with was totally okay,
good upstanding Jew, okay except that we slept together but other than
that totally okay fine", so then רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua, *Rabbi Yehoshua*
says we don't believe her. לא מפיה אנו חיין *lo mipia anu
hayin*. And here there's an objective ספק Safek *safek*, she has no
idea, and he says no problem. So how do you reconcile this?
אמר ליה Amar lei, *Amar lei*, היכי השתא *heichi hashta*, how can
you compare that? התם אישה נישאת בודקת ונישאת *Hatam isha nises bodeket
venises*. There a woman who gets married checks ahead of time before
getting married. הכא אישה מזנה בודקת ומזנה *Hacha isha mezana bodeket umezana*?
But a woman before she commits an act of you know of
זנות *znut*, of like what's the word not
licentiousness licentiousness anyway she's gonna check before she סתם stam *stam* sleeps
around? So meaning what? That this that this case about the אלמנה
Almana *almana* from you know she married this man who might have
been a חלל chalal *chalal*, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to
say if she married the guy we're going to assume she'll check
out his status before she married him which is a pretty funny
assumption because you know if she's not a... maybe she doesn't care
about חללה *chalala*, that only affects כהונה *kehuna* status, right? All right
maybe he's a חלל chalal *chalal* big deal so then my child
won't be a כהן kohen *kohen* what do I care right? So
but nevertheless the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to say here's this
child that based on what happened with his mother and some doubtful
גט *get* he might be a חלל chalal *chalal* we're going to
assume that if a woman marries her she's okay because we'll assume
she'll have checked into it. I mean how do you even know
that there's that you could check into it that there's like enough
evidence to be discovered to figure out what the story is? But
that's why we're going to say she's okay we'll assume she checked
into it. Whereas in רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua *Rabbi Yehoshua*'s case where
she סתם *stam* slept with some random guy we're not going to
assume that she clarified what the situation was and therefore just because
she tells us the guy was okay how do you know the
guy was okay? You were סתם *stam* sleeping around. So it also
seems like there's a certain possible like moral judgment here right? If
you're going ahead and doing this activity of being מזנה *mezane* and
sleeping around we're not going to give that much weight to your
claim that you know you know what the... she doesn't want to
imperil her future generation. Well
that's true also. Okay so anyway that's the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s answer.
Here we believe her less because she סתם *stam* was sleeping around.
אמר רבא Rava *Amar Rava* says רבא *Rava* דרבי יהושע אדרבי יהושע
קשיא דרבן גמליאל אדרבן גמליאל לא קשיא *deRabbi Yehoshua a'deRabbi Yehoshua kashya
deRabban Gamliel a'deRabban Gamliel lo kashya*? What it's only a problem that
רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua *Rabbi Yehoshua* seems to contradict himself not רבן
גמליאל Rabban Gamliel *Rabban Gamliel*? רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel *Rabban Gamliel* also
seems to contradict himself. והקתני סיפא *Ve'hakatani seifa* the end of that
משנה mishnah. *Mishna* says אמר להם רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel *Amar lahem
Rabban Gamliel*, רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel *Rabban Gamliel* said to רבי יהושע
Rabbi Yehoshua *Rabbi Yehoshua* and רבי Rabbi, יהודה בן בתירה *Rabbi Yehuda
ben Beteira* who gave this testimony: קבלנו עדותכם *Kibalnu edutchem* we accept
your testimony I believe what you're saying is true but אבל aval,
מה נעשה *aval ma na'aseh* what should we do שהרי גזר רבן
יוחנן בן זכאי *sheharei gazar Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai*, רבן יוחנן בן
זכאי *Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai* made an edict שלא להושיב בית דין
על כך *shelo lehoshiv beit din al kach* that a בית דין
*beit din* should not rule this way should not rule that such
a woman is permissible to כהנים Kohanim, *kohanim*. Why shouldn't the בית
דין *beit din* rule this way? שהכהנים שומעים לכם לרחק אבל לא
לקרב *Shehakohanim shom'im lachem lerachek aval lo l'karev* because כהנים *kohanim* are
so scrupulous about their יחוס *yichus* that if you tell them oh
don't marry this woman don't marry that woman they'll listen to you.
They'll listen to a חומרא *chumra*. But if you tell them oh
this woman is okay they won't listen to you. What do you
mean she's okay there's a ספק *safek*. Okay there's a lot of
people like that they'll accept any חומרא *chumra* they won't accept a
קולא *kula*. There's a lot of people the opposite they'll accept every
קולא *kula* and no חומרא *chumra*. Anyway so he says look technically
you might be right but we can't rule that way. Now the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* sees this as a problem because although if you
and I read it it's saying okay he agrees in principle he's
just saying that in practice it won't work but the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara*'s understanding well if in practice it won't work it sounds like
he's saying don't go ahead פוסק *paskening* this way don't פוסק *pasken*
in a way that nobody's going to listen to you. But in
our case in the משנה *Mishna* when you say to her who
was that man you just slept with and she says it was
so and so and I'm okay to marry a כהן kohen *kohen*,
רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel *Rabban Gamliel* says fine she's okay to marry
a כהן kohen. *kohen*. So you're prepared to פוסק *pasken* about a
woman who has a questionable status that she's prepared to marry a
כהן kohen. *kohen*. How come here you're not? So it's got a
problem in both directions. So what's the answer? אלא ella, אמר רבא
*Ella amar Rava* so rather רבא *Rava* says דרבן גמליאל אדרבן גמליאל
לא קשיא *deRabban Gamliel a'deRabban Gamliel lo kashya*. Here's where רבן גמליאל
Rabban Gamliel *Rabban Gamliel* doesn't contradict himself. התם ברי הכא שמא *Hatam
bari hacha
shema*. The reason רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel *Rabban Gamliel* says you believe
her in our case where she סתם *stam* slept with a guy
was because she says I know what the status of that guy
was and רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel *Rabban Gamliel* says fine we believe
her. So she's making a definite claim we're prepared to believe her
even if and maybe we'll be prepared to tell the כהנים *kohanim*
stop having all your crazy חומרות *chumrot*. She says what we believe
what she says and we go by that. But there's a definite
claim there somebody is saying they know. Somebody is saying they know
we're prepared to believe her. to go behind that, we're prepared to
back that. That's the case of the משנה *Mishnah*. One minute, הכא
*hacha* שמא
*shema*—here however, he doesn't know what the status is of this guy.
He married a guy who was a ספק חלל safek chalal, *safek
challal*, she has no idea, she's not even claiming she knows what
his status is. So in that case, even if we believe that
his status was okay, we're not going to be prepared to rule
that way; the כהנים *Kohanim* won't listen to us because nobody is
claiming to have clear knowledge. That's his position. Of course once you
say that, that for him it's an idea of a שמא *shema*,
then it's harder to make the claim before of the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* that אשה בודקת *isha bodekes*, that the woman checked his status,
because we're whole saying here that she has no idea about his
status in this case. So now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s going to
modify what it says about ר' יהושע *Rabbi Yehoshua* as well. לר'
יהושע דר' יהושע נמי לא קשיא *le'Rabbi Yehoshua de'Rabbi Yehoshua nami lo
kashya*, therefore ר' יהושע *Rabbi Yehoshua* also didn't contradict himself. It's not
because here we're assuming the woman looked into it, but התם חד
ספיקא *hasam chad sefeika* in the case in the משנה *Mishnah* which
she סתם *stam* slept with a guy, there was only one doubt.
So therefore even though she's claiming she knows his status, we don't
believe her. There's a possibility he was a פסול pasul. *posul* and
there's a doubt, and we won't believe her. הכא *hacha* but this
case about the אמנת אישה *amanas isha*, תרי ספיקי *trei sefeika*, there
are two doubts. So what are the two doubts? So that's what
I was telling you before; either it really is just one doubt
that went two generations, right, was the mother a גרושה grusha אלמנה
*grusha almana* and therefore was the son a חלל chalal, *challal* or
חללה *challala* and therefore was the wife of the son a חלל
chalal *challal* or חללה *challala*? So it's the same question but it
went two generations. Somehow that makes it—that makes it more sort of,
you know, more vague. Like something that happened already a generation ago,
it's—somehow that makes it easier. Or the other thing which רש"י Rashi
*Rashi* said was that there really are two questions. We don't know
whose son it was, and even if we knew it was the
second man's son, we don't know if the woman was a גרושה
Gerusha אלמנה *grusha almana*. And now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* just spells
out therefore how the רבן גמליאל *Rabban Gamliel* and ר' יהושע *Rabbi
Yehoshua* break down. It says like this: הלכך לרבן גמליאל אלים ליה
ברי *hilkach le'Rabban Gamliel alim lei bari*, for רבן גמליאל *Rabban Gamliel*
her claim that I definitely am telling you what the status of
that man was is so strong דאפילו בחד ספיקא נמי מכשר *de'afilu
be'chad sefeika nami machshir*, that even when there's just one doubt—we know
she slept with a guy, there's one question, what was the status
of the guy—and even for example if it was רוב rov, פסולין
*rov psulin*, her claim that I'm telling you here was his story
is strong enough to say we're going to go by what she
says even in the face of one doubt. נמי מכשר *nami machshir*.
וקיל ליה שמא *vekil lei shema*, but as soon as she says
I don't know his status, right, in the case of the אמנת
אישה *amanas isha*, דאפילו בספק ספיקא נמי פסל *de'afilu be'sfek sefeika nami
posel*. Once we don't have her claim, even if objectively there's like
a double doubt or a doubt in a previous generation and it's
a weaker doubt, too bad, you're stuck if you don't have a
ברי *bari* claim. So that's רבן גמליאל *Rabban Gamliel*'s position. So in
the משנה *Mishnah* he says I believe her, she's making a claim.
In this case of the משנה *Mishnah* in עדיות *Eduyos*, she's saying
כהנים *Kohanim* aren't going to listen to us because once she's not
making a claim, even if it's this vaguer double doubt, we're not
going to be prepared to say she's okay. That's רבן גמליאל *Rabban
Gamliel*. ור' יהושע *ve'Rabbi Yehoshua* is the opposite. ר' יהושע אלים ליה
חד ספיקא *Rabbi Yehoshua alim lei chad sefeika*, for ר' יהושע *Rabbi
Yehoshua* having one doubt is very weighty. In our משנה *Mishnah*, דאפילו
בברי נמי פסל *de'afilu be'bari nami posel*, even when she says here's
what I'm telling you, he was okay, doesn't matter. It's a single
doubt, we ignore—right, ר' יהושע *Rabbi Yehoshua*'s whole point is לא מפי
אנו חיים *lo mipi anu chayim*, he basically completely disregards her claim.
So I'm going to disregard your claim, I'm going to look at
it objectively. So objectively in the משנה *Mishnah* there's one doubt. One
doubt, you've got—you know, that's a question. You have a questionable status.
וקיל ליה ספק ספיקא *vekil lei sfek sefeika*, but when it's a
double doubt, you know, or it's a doubt in a previous generation,
that's objectively weaker. דאפילו בשמא נמי מכשר *de'afilu be'shema nami machshir*, then
for even when she says I don't know, and once it's a
weaker doubt, we're going to say it's okay. So this is a
nice little distillation basically what's saying is: רבן גמליאל *Rabban Gamliel* says
I all go by what she claims, נאמנת ne'emenes, *ne'emenes*. Her claim
is so weighty that even if it's just one question: who did
you sleep with, and even in the case of רוב rov פסולין
*rov psulin* I'm prepared to believe her. But when she doesn't make
a claim, a concrete claim, then I'm going to say, well, even
if there's a weaker doubt, I'm going to say she has a
questionable status. ור' יהושע *ve'Rabbi Yehoshua* is the opposite. He completely disregards
her statement, but he says a strong doubt like in our משנה
*Mishnah*, she's got a questionable status. A weak doubt like the case
of אמנת אישה *amanas isha*, her status will be okay. Do you
had a question?
In עדיות *Eduyos*, are they testifying about a מעשה שהיה *maaseh shehayah*
or about what they heard in בית המדרש *beis hamidrash*?
Yeah, so sometimes both. Like sometimes it's about—often it's about testifying about
how other rabbis פסק *psak*-ed. Like, you know, sometimes they say like
they accepted the testimony of these two weavers who said that, you
know, there was a case and well that would be a מעשה
שהיה *maaseh shehayah* or testimony about how some rabbi פסק *psak*-s. Right,
but here
it's—right here it says—that's a good question. Like when it says על
אמנת אישה שהיא *al amanas isha shehi*, I assumed it meant that
they were communicating a tradition of פסק *psak*, not of a specific
case, but I think you have like יש ויש *yeish veyeish*. Yeah,
I don't remember, you know, I think there are both cases where
they communicate a testimony about what the פסק *psak*—what abstract פסק *psak*
had been and sometimes it definitely is testimony about concrete cases of
פסק *psak*. Did you—do you think it would make a difference here
or
you're just—Well, I mean I was wondering why does the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* not just answer, so...
those were the particulars of those cases,
but yeah, so that doesn't mean?
Yeah, but then it wouldn't have been incorporated in an עדות of
if there was not some sense that you could like make a
principle from it, right, it wouldn't have been like incorporated there. You
have to so if it is basically saying, well, those were the
particulars of the case, so that's what we're doing, we're identifying what
was the what particulars of the case made it different. Okay. So
now we've introduced this idea of אלמנת עיסה, almanas isa, which is
a woman with questionable status and she doesn't know her own status,
but the doubt is more, you know, is vague-er. Okay. תנו רבנן
tana rabanan and that's what we're going to look at now. So,
איזו היא אלמנת עיסה? eizu hi almanas isa? What is this case
of אלמנת עיסה? almanas isa? כל שאין בה לא משום ממזרות, kol
she-ein bah lo mishum mamzerus, there's no question about whether she slept
with a ממזר, mamzer, ולא משום נתינות velo mishum nesinus or a
נתין, nesin, ולא משום עבדי מלכים velo mishum avdei melachim or with
an עבד. eved. The reason it's עבדי מלכים avdei melachim is because
like, yeah, the גמרא Gemara refers to עבדי שלמה avdei Shlomo and
they were very powerful, or maybe הורדוס Hordus was seen as a
slave and then for somebody that could have basically
have made women sleep with him. So it doesn't have those doubts.
So what doubt does it have? So presumably the doubt we said
before was a doubt of status of a חלל, chalal not a
question about, you know, about some of these like prohibited things, but
about whether the, you know, the person's mother had slept with a,
you know, was a, had she been a גרושה Gerusha and did
she and then she slept with a כהן. kohen. Okay. So the
גמרא Gemara later is going to ask what difference does it make?
Once there's a question of some prohibited act, who cares if it
was the fact that the mother slept with a כהן kohen or
the mother who was a ספק גרושה safek grusha slept with a
כהן Kohen. or maybe she slept with a ספק ממזר, safek mamzer,
who cares? Once it's a forbidden act. So but for whatever reason
it's saying that it's only, it's not when those doubts are present,
only when a חלל chalal, doubt is present. The rest of this
דף daf is going to unpack this ברייתא braisa because it's a
complicated ברייתא. braisa. Okay, so with those, we're not talking about those
doubts. אמר רבי מאיר, amar rabbi meir, said Rabbi Meir, שמעתי, shamati,
I heard, כל שאין בה אחד מכל אלו משיאין לכהונה. kol she-ein
bah echad mi-kol elu masi la-kehunah. When you don't have any of
those problems, you can marry the woman off to a כהן. Kohen.
Okay, that was sort of exactly what we were saying, that that
woman is an אלמנת עיסה almanas isa and can marry a כהן.
Kohen. So what did Rabbi Meir add? Not clear. It doesn't sound
like it, sounds like he's saying the exact same thing we just
said. Oh, here's a case where this אלמנת עיסה almanas isa doesn't
have a, is okay if she doesn't have any of these problems.
And then Rabbi Meir says, yeah, I heard that such a woman
could marry a כהן. Kohen. Okay.
All right, no, this is not being brought into רבן גמליאל and
רבי יהושע. Rabbi Yehoshua. רבי שמעון בן אלעזר משום רבי מאיר, Rabbi
Shimon ben Elazar mishum rabbi meir, then רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi
Shimon ben Elazar says in the name of Rabbi Meir, וכן היה
רבי שמעון בן מנסיא אומר כדבריו ve-chen hayah Rabbi Shimon ben Menasya
omer ke-divrav and רבי שמעון בן מנסיא Rabbi Shimon ben Menasya said
the same thing, איזו היא אלמנת עיסה? eizu hi almanas isa? No,
what's an אלמנת עיסה? almanas isa? כל שנטמע בה ספק חלל. kol
she-nitma bah safek chalal.
Anybody that was mixed in with her, this is an ע ayin
and not an א aleph of נטמע, nitma, which means somebody that
was intermixed with her, some doubtful חלל chalal status, like I gave
you the example before. Okay, fine. Again, how's that different? Because חלל
Challal was presumably that's what we were talking about because we haven't
been mentioning חלל, Challal, we've been, we said not ממזר, mamzer, not
נתין, nesin, not עבד, eved, so presumably the whole point was a
חלל Challal point. So now you got three people seemingly to say
the exact same thing. And then it says, מכירין ישראל ממזרים שביניהם
ואין מכירין חללים שביניהם. makkirin Yisrael mamzerim she-beineihem ve-ein makkirin chalalim she-beineihem.
The Jewish people know the ממזרים mamzerim among them and not the
חללים chalalim among them. And how that's relevant exactly how? Not clear.
Okay, the גמרא Gemara is going to understand that that actually is
going to mean that the
opposite,
right,
because if you don't know who the חללים chalalim are, so, well,
also because
right,
exactly.
If there was a ספק whether the woman had sex with a
ממזר, mamzer, then you would probably know because we know who the
ממזרים mamzerim are. So therefore since we don't know, the fact that
we don't know could make us assume that it wasn't a ממזר.
mamzer. So you know, so that would actually incline to be more
lenient by a ספק ממזר. safek mamzer. Whereas if it was a,
this is the way רש"י understands it because the גמרא Gemara is
going to read that this contradicts the previous statement. Whereas if the
woman had sex with a guy that was a ספק חלל, Safek
Challal we would have to be strict because he might genuinely be
a חלל Challal, and we might not know about it. So the
first three statements seem to be saying the exact same thing and
then the last statement seems to be saying the opposite and it's
said by the same person. So what does any of this mean?
So let's take a look. So that's what we're going to spend
the rest of the דף daf doing, figuring out. אמר מר: amar
mar: איזו היא אלמנת עיסה? eizu hi almanas isa? כל שאין בה
לא משום ממזרות ולא משום נתינות ולא משום עבדי מלכים. kol she-ein
bah lo mishum mamzerus velo mishum nesinus velo mishum avdei melachim. החלל
כשר. ha-chalal kasher. So
if there was a question about whether the mother slept with a
חלל, Challal which is sort of what we've been talking about, or
by the way, you know, the son was a חלל Challal etc.,
the example we gave, whether the mother was a ספק גרושה, safek
grusha, it'd be כשר. kasher. So the גמרא Gemara says, מאי שנא
הני דאורייתא חלל נמי דאורייתא? mai shena hanei de-oraisa chalal nami de-oraisa?
Why
if there's a question that maybe there was an act of sleeping
with one of these guys, ממזר, mamzer, נתין, nesin, עבד, eved, that
that, oh, then it would be a problem? Because that's a possible
biblical violation, that is a, I mean if they did it, it
was a biblical violation, the woman sleeping with them. So a גרושה
Gerusha sleeping with a כהן kohen, for example is also a biblical
violation. Why? Why is the doubt about a חלל Challal, better than
the doubt about any of these? So the גמרא Gemara says, right,
everybody gets that meaning? Sleeping with a חלל, Challal, for a woman
to sleep with a חלל Challal is not a problem. I mean,
the kids won't be כהנים, but there's no איסור Issur to sleep
with he becomes a חלל, Challal but there's no violation. The violation,
but what creates the חלל Challal, comes through a violation. A חלל
Challal is created because a woman slept, let's say a גרושה slept
with a כהן. kohen, Okay? So the גמרא Gemara is saying is
if this child here is a ספק חלל Safek Challal, or this
אלמנה, this woman was married to a man who was a ספק
חלל, Safek Challal, etc., so if that means that there's some possible
violation that occurred in the past, the mother was a גרושה or
ספק גרושה Safek Gerusha slept with a כהן. kohein, So why is
that a case where, oh, in that case, there's a question if
he's a חלל, Challal, we'll say ספק it's okay? Question if he
came from a ממזר Mamzer or an עבד Eved or whatever, then
we're going to say no good. Either way, it's a question whether
some violation was done. Why are we going to be more lenient
in one case than in the other? Okay, so let's take a
look. So מאי שנא הני דאורייתא, חלל נמי דאורייתא. Mai shena hanei
De'oraisa, challal nami De'oraisa.
Question number one. Question number two: how does this opinion differ from
the opinions that come after? ותו, אמר רבי מאיר: שמעתי כל שאין
בה אחד מכל אלו משיאין לכהונה. Vesu, amar Rabbi Meir: Shamati kol
she'ein bah echad mikol elu masi'in likhunah. When you have none of
these problems of נתין, Nasin, ממזר Mamzer and עבד, Eved, no other
no questions, the woman can marry a כהן. היינו תנא קמא. Hainu
Tanna Kamma. That's what we just said, that when you don't have
these questions, the woman, even though there's a ספק חלל, Safek Challal
the woman can marry a כהן. It's exactly the same thing. ותו,
Vesu, number three. רבי שמעון בן אלעזר אומר משום רבי מאיר, Rabbi
Shimon ben Elazar omer mishum Rabbi Meir, a different opinion in the
name of רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. וכן היה רבי שמעון בן מנסיא
אומר כדבריו: איזו היא אלמנת עיסה? כל שנתערב בה ספק חלל. Vekhein
hayah Rabbi Shimon ben Menasya omer kidvarav: Eizo hi almanas issah? Kol
shenisarev bah safek challal.
Anybody that has a doubt for חלל, Challal. which also seems to
be the same point. And then he says: מכירין ישראל ממזרים שביניהם,
ואין מכירין חללים שביניהם. Makkirin Yisrael mamzeirim shebeineihem, ve'ein makkirin challallim shebeineihem.
We know the ממזרים, Mamzeirim, we don't know the חללים. Challallim. והא
אמרת רישא, Veha amart reisha, you just said חלל כשר, Challal kasher,
that if it's a doubtful חלל chalal, it's כשר. Kasher. Now you
say we don't know who the חללים Challallim are, so therefore a
doubtful חלל chalal should be more of a problem. So none of
this makes sense. You have three different opinions that are really sound
like they're the exact same opinion, and then you have a last
line which seems to be a contradiction of what you said a
second ago. So אמר רבי יוחנן. Amar Rabbi Yochanan. So we're going
to have to introduce a whole new discourse into this conversation in
order to make sense out of this ברייתא. Braisa. So here's what
the other whole missing secret secret ingredient that we didn't that we
didn't mention. אמר רבי יוחנן: ממזר צווח וחלל שותק איכא בינייהו. Amar
Rabbi Yochanan: Mamzer tzove'ach vechallal shotek ika beiniyahu.
The difference between these different opinions has to do with a case
that if you call a guy a ממזר, Mamzer, he yells and
he complains, whereas if you call him a חלל, chalal he's not
going to say he doesn't say anything, he just listens and doesn't
respond. So meaning what רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, we're going to spell
it out, but what רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is going to introduce
is it's not just a question of what the ספק is, there's
also a question of how does the person react when you say
when you basically call him by this name. And if he is
silent, does his lack of reaction indicate that he concedes that that
is his status? Okay, now that's pretty funny because you know sometimes
whatever people go around and you know they get called certain things
because of certain rumors exist and everybody starts calling them names and
then they get a little tired of always sort of you know
responding and reacting or whatever and they just sort of bear it
and go on with their lives. You know and now we're going
to say that the silence is is interpreted as as an admission,
especially in cases where you know we like this case of ספק
חלל safek chalal, where presumably we know the objective basis for the
doubt. Why should his silence tell us one way or the other
way? What does he know about whether his mother was a גרושה
or אלמנה when she slept with the father? But that's the new
thing we're going to introduce to give us a basis for understanding
what this מחלוקת תנאים machlokes Tanna'im is about. So let's take a
look.
It seems the objection would logically apply to us because we've always
been taking the husband's word as a, you know, as a valid
protest. He has no objective basis.
Oh
when he says when he makes a claim about what his wife
did and he doesn't really know. That's true. Okay, so let's see
what the גמרא Gemara says. It says תנא קמא סבר: כל פסול
דקרי ליה ושתיק, פסול. Tanna Kamma savar: Kol pasul dekarei lei veshaseik,
pasul.
Any type of invalidity that you call a guy by and he's
silent, we assume that his silence is an admission and he's invalid.
Okay, so therefore if you called him a ממזר Mamzer or son
of an עבד Eved or a נתין Nasin and he was silent,
you would say oh therefore he's a problem. So if you called
him a חלל chalal and he was silent, presumably it would also
be a problem. So let's take a look. והכי קאמר תנא קמא.
Vehaichi ka'amar Tanna Kamma. Here's what the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma is
saying. איזו היא אלמנת עיסה? Eizo hi almanas issah? What is this
אלמנת עיסה Almanas issah where we say the woman married to this
man is okay? כל שאין בה לא שתוק ממזרות. Kol she'ein bah
lo shetok mamzeirus.
Any case where by her, but it really means here by the
man she was married to,
was not a case where you called the guy a ממזר Mamzer
and he was silent. ולא שתוק נתינות, Velo shetok nesinus, or you
called the guy a נתין Nasin and he was silent. ולא שתוק
עבדי מלכים, Velo shetok avdei melachim, or you called him the son
of a slave and he was silent. ולא שתוק חלל, Velo shetok
challal, or funny because the one thing not mentioned by the תנא
קמא Tanna Kamma is חלל, chalal and by and now we're inserting
it in. And not that he was silent about a חלל. chalal,
So the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma what he's saying is who's a
ספק אלמנה? Safek Almana? doesn't have any of these problems, he doesn't
mean to say if it's not ממזר mamzer and נתין netin it's,
it's okay even though it's חלל, chalal, חלל chalal is not a
problem, like that's the way we read it. But the תנא Tanna
was saying like, ממזר, mamzer, נתין, netin, those would be real issues,
but ספק חלל, chalal? that's not a problem. So the גמרא Gemara
is saying, no, no, no, that's not how you to read it.
He's, the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma is not trying to distinguish חלל
chalal from anything else. What the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma is saying
is, אלמנת עיסה almanat isa is okay when it's just a doubt
that we have and we don't know what the status is, then
we'll be lenient. Okay, but it's not when any of these names
were called on the person and the person was silent, including the
חלל chalal name. We didn't mention חלל chalal. but that was implicit.
So what it means is, an אלמנת עיסה almanat isa is okay
when it doesn't have these problems, it means when the person was
not silent in response to being called these names. If he was
silent, then we've got a problem. But if he was never, if
he was not silent when called these names, then we can be
lenient because we have a doubt about the status and we'll be
lenient and we'll assume it's okay.
Yes, assume that everybody knows their status.
Right, that's the thing. It assumes, A, that everybody's going to object
and, B, that everybody knows their status or that people would object
if they, if they weren't certain about their status. It makes a
lot of funny assumptions. That's true, absolutely.
Does the גמרא Gemara doubt about that assumption? I mean what...
Well, that's where the גמרא is right now. Let's see as the
גמרא continues. But yes, that's, you know, in order to make sense
of this ברייתא braita we're making a lot of big assumptions in
terms of, you know, how people react when they're called names. Okay.
Okay, so that's the תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma. So the real point
of the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma is not to single out חלל,
chalal, the real point of the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma is to
say it's okay as long as the guy wasn't called a name
and silent about it. So קאמר ליה רבי מאיר ka-amar lei Rabbi
Meir and then רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir responds to this and says,
הנהו דקפסילי בקהל, hanehu de-ka-pasil lei be-kahal,
you know what, those that you mentioned, not the חלל, chalal, is
true, that if he's silent and this say that would invalidate him,
his silence is taken as an admission. אבל שתוק חלל, aval shetuk
chalal, but if you called the guy a חלל chalal, and he
didn't respond, כשר, kasher,
that would not invalidate him. והא דשתוק, ve-ha de-shatok,
so why is he silent? Why isn't he responding when you call
him a חלל? chalal משום דלא איכפת ליה, mishum de-lo ikhpat lei,
because he doesn't care. Because remember what I said, a
חלל chalal, derives from a forbidden union, but there's no problem of
a חלל chalal to marry any other woman. So if you said,
you know, you come from a ממזר mamzer or an עבד eved
or whatever, then, oh my god, that if this makes this guy
a ממזר, mamzer, this makes this guy, he won't be able to
marry a woman. So therefore he's going to respond. So the way
we've now set it up is that the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma
says, okay, this אלמנת עיסה almanat isa is when there's a doubt
but not when the guy is silent. If the guy is silent
about anything you take that as an admission. Comes along רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir and says, except if he's silent about חלל. chalal If
he's silent about חלל, chalal you don't take it as an admission.
He doesn't bother responding because it's not going to really hurt his
status and he's not going to therefore say anything. Okay, again, none
of that is in the words of the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma
or רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, but that's what we're saying. So now
they're debating being whether a guy called a חלל, chalal? is he
silent, is that seen as an admission or not? And then we
come along with the third opinion, דקאמר ליה רבי שמעון בן אלעזר
לתנא קמא דרבי מאיר, de-ka-amar lei Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar le-Tanna Kamma
de-Rabbi Meir, that
רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar says to the first
תנא קמא Tanna Kamma of רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, meaning there was
first a רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and then was רבי שמעון בן
אלעזר Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar in the name of רבי מאיר. Rabbi
Meir. So רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar is saying
to the one who just said straight state what רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir said, אשמיע לך דמכשר רבי מאיר בשתיקה, ashmiya lach de-machshir Rabbi
Meir be-shtika, if you heard that there was cases that רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir said if you're silent it's okay, לא דקרי ליה חלל
ושתוק, lo de-kari lei chalal ve-shatok, not like you're saying when the
guy was silent in response to being called a חלל, chalal that
you said that that would not be an admission. אלא, the opposite,
דקרי ליה ממזר ושתוק. de-kari lei mamzer ve-shatok.
Only if they called the guy a ממזר mamzer and he was
silent, that's seen as a non-admission. That's pretty heavy. You think you
call a guy a ממזר mamzer and he's silent, you'd think that
that's a pretty bad thing to be called, you'd think that was
an admission. So why is he reversing it? והא דשתוק, ve-ha de-shatok,
so why is he silent if he's being called a ממזר? mamzer?
סבר ממזר קלא
אית ליה, savar mamzer kala it lei, he says like the last
line: People know who the ממזרים mamzerim are. So why do I
have to respond? Pretty funny idea. Why do I have to respond
if I'm being called a ממזר? mamzer? We all have a list
of the ממזרים mamzerim and I'm not on that list, I'm not
going to bother to respond. But if they're calling me a חלל
chalal and people don't know who the חללים chalalim are, I'd better
speak up because I don't want to get suspected about being a
חלל, chalal nobody will know the facts. But they'll, but they know
the facts about ממזרים mamzerim because we all know the ממזרים mamzerim
so I don't have to respond. Pretty funny response, one minute. Okay,
סבר ממזר קלא אית ליה. savar mamzer kala it lei. אבל ממזר...
aval mamzer... okay,
so that's the position. So therefore he says, מכירין ישראל ממזרים שביניהם
מכירין חללים שביניהם. makirin Yisrael mamzerim she-beinehem makirin chalalim she-beinehem. Again, meaning,
yeah, so כל שנטמע בה ספק חלל kol she-nitma bah safek chalal
is not so clear, but he basically saying that being silent about
a חלל chalal actually is a problem. If he's silent, if it's
a question of a חלל chalal without silence, that's the אלמנת עיסה.
almanat isa. But if you want to talk about being silent, being
silent about a חלל chalal is actually דווקא davka a problem and
being silent about a ממזר mamzer is not a problem. My God,
that's the first... I gotta say the first position makes a lot
more sense, right? If you ask like what will somebody respond to,
they'll say you want to call me a חלל? chalal Big deal.
Like it's not going to impact my status even if people do
believe you. I'm not going to go ahead and fight you, whatever.
You call a guy a ממזר, mamzer, right, you expect people to
speak up. Okay, yes.
Because up until now he hasn't been able to eat תרומה terumah
anyway, right? Because meaning what's happening until now? You don't even want
him to get married, but you know when he was because I
mean if.
Yeah, that's a good question. Yeah, it's a good question in terms
of like תרומה terumah if he's a חלל chalal and what's been
his. Yep, yep, it's a good question. I don't know. It's a
good question.
What, can a חלל chalal. marry a בת כהן?
bas kohen? A חלל chalal can marry, yeah, I mean the child
won't be a כהן, but yes, yes. Okay, so the גמרא says
like this.
Okay, so okay, so אבל, so therefore the second one says ironically
that being silent about a ממזר mamzer is not an admission, being
silent about a חלל chalal, is. אבל ממזר וצוווח חלל ושותק פסול.
aval mamzer u'tzovei'ach chalal v'shoseik pasul. If you call him a חלל
chalal and he, I got ממזר mamzer instead of, חלל chalal and
he's silent, that is an admission because people don't know who the
חללים chalalim are, so being silent is admission. And interestingly, yeah, that's
what's so again funny about the whole thing is that how's he
supposed to know? But interestingly, if he's a ממזר mamzer and he
objects, that actually creates more of a problem. If he's a ממזר
mamzer and he's silent, he basically goes, why do I have to
respond to this idiot, everybody knows who the ממזרים mamzeirim are. But
somehow if he's a ממזר mamzer and he objects, we sort of
see like well why are you objecting and making such a fuss?
By objecting you're actually drawing attention to the whole situation and somehow,
again this is quite ironic, if you're going to object that's actually
going to make it suspect that you are a ממזר, mamzer, which
I feel is very funny and it came out of left field.
I mean the
possibility that he's silent is more suspect. Yeah, it's very funny about
that.
Yeah,
right. So I really don't understand here how why the גמרא is
assuming that all of a sudden that the objecting creates a bigger
problem. Okay, והאי דאשתק, v'hai d'ishtik, and it sort of jumps over
the ממזר וצוווח, mamzer u'tzovei'ach, it really is focusing on the חלל
ושותק. chalal v'shoseik. והאי דאשתק סבר, v'hai d'ishtik savar, and the reason
he's being silent as a as a חלל chalal is because סבר
savar מסתייד דלא מפקו לי מקהל. mistayid d'lo mafkei lei mikahal. Look,
better to just be quiet and have them think I'm a doubtful
חלל rather than to make a fuss about it, and if I
make a fuss about it, they'll know that I'm a definite חלל.
So you know, so his silence therefore is, whereas by the case
of ממזר mamzer being silent we assume he's silent because he figures
why bother, everybody knows who the ממזרים mamzeirim are anyway. But by
the חלל we say that he's silent and he's saying, and that
we're going to see that as an admission. Now why doesn't he
just סתם say the silence is an admission? But anyway the גמרא
adds to the fact that that, and I'm not going to bother
to object because being silent will just turn the doubt into, you
know what is it, better to you know have people think you're
a fool than to open up your mouth and remove all doubt.
So okay, so they say that his silence is more beneficial.
Right, right, יפה שתיקותיך
מיפה מדיבורייך.
yafeh
shtikusayich mi'yafeh midiburayich.
Right, right, יפה שתיקותיך, yafeh shtikusayich, right, יפה מדיבורייך. yafeh midiburayich. So
anyway, so there he's going to say I'd better just keep my
mouth shut. But actually if anything, that just underscores the fact that
we do think he's a doubtful חלל, okay, and therefore because, and
therefore he is פסול. pasul Again why the fact that he speaks
up as a ממזר mamzer makes it a problem, I don't know.
But the real focus here is on the, is on the חלל
who's silent. Okay. תני חדא, tani chada, we taught one ברייתא. braisa.
רבי יוסי אומר שותק ממזר כשר שתוק ממזר כשר
שתוק חלל פסול, Rabbi Yossi omer shoseik mamzer kasher shtuk mamzer kasher
shtuk chalal pasul, that a somebody who does not respond to being
called a ממזר mamzer is כשר, kasher, if he doesn't respond to
being called a חלל he's invalid. That's like we sort of just
said according to the second opinion of רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. ותני
אידך, v'tani idach, and another ברייתא braisa that says שתוק חלל כשר
שתוק ממזר פסול. shtuk chalal kasher shtuk mamzer pasul. The opposite. Silence
about a חלל is כשר kasher because like why bother speaking up,
it doesn't really affect my status anyway; being silent about a ממזר
mamzer is פסול because that does affect your status and your silence
is an admission. That was the first opinion of רבי מאיר. Rabbi
Meir. לא קשיא הא תנא קמא אליבא דרבי מאיר הא רבי שמעון
בן אלעזר אליבא דרבי מאיר, la kashya ha tanna kamma aliba d'Rabbi
Meir ha Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar aliba d'Rabbi Meir, which is what
the גמרא says, it just maps onto that. So presumably introducing this
whole idea of being being silent is we have a ברייתא braisa
that actually introduces that factor as well, and that's what we're reading
into this whole discussion of אלמנת עיסא almanas issa in order to
explain the range of opinions that are going on there. Okay, so
that was a little bit complicated with all of that, but what
is interesting is that that according to רבי, first of all that
the question about being called a name and being silent could have
some relevance even in cases where there might be other reasons you
didn't respond and you might not know your status. But going back
to the debate of רבן גמליאל and רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua the
גמרא says רבן גמליאל's basically what his whole point is is is
that נאמנת, she makes a definite claim and we believe her. If
she herself doesn't know, then he's more prepared to say she's got
a questionable status, can't marry כהן, even if it's like a double
doubt or a more abstract doubt. And רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua, is
the opposite. He says I completely discount her statement, but I will
weigh how serious the doubt is. And therefore in a case of
a more abstract or of a double doubt, I'll be prepared to
say that she's okay. All right, let's start the next משנה. אמר
רבי יוסי, amar Rabbi Yossi, said רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yossi. מעשה בתינוקת,
ma'aseh b'tinokes, there was a story about a young woman. I mean
תינוקת tinoket again, it doesn't mean an infant, but who knows, probably
a girl, an underaged girl. שירדה למלאות מים מן העין. sheyarda limlot
mayim min ha-ayin. She went to draw water from the well. ונענסה,
v'ne'ensa, and she was raped. אמר רבי יוחנן בן נורי, Amar Rabbi
Yochanan ben Nuri, so this is a similar question except as opposed
to the woman
who willingly slept with another man and we're trying to figure out
who was the man she slept with, here's a question of not
knowing the identity of the rapist. And therefore is this rapist if
he was a non-Jew or whatever the woman is פסולה לכהונה. psula
l'kehuna. If he's not, the woman is כשרה לכהונה, kshaira l'kehuna, right?
She's an unmarried girl.
So it's the same question of who is the man you slept
with but here she has no knowledge and here she was raped.
Okay. So אמר רבי יוחנן בן נורי אם רוב אנשי עיר משיאים
לכהונה הרי זו תינשא לכהונה. Amar Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri im rov
anshei ir masi'im l'kehuna harei zu tinasei l'kehuna. If most of the
people in the city would be, you could marry women that they
slept with to a כהן, meaning that they're A, they're Jewish, B,
most of them are
not
ממזרים, mamzeirim, חללים, chalalim, נתינים, nesinim, etc., which is going to be
always the case, I mean, that you're going to have רוב כשרים
rov kshairim if they're Jewish. So then her status is okay. So
here we're going by רוב, rov right? Remember the גמרא said that
within רבן גמליאל and רבי יהושע when she says she knows who
the guy is she slept with, רבן גמליאל was lenient even if
רוב rov. is פסולים. psulim. And רבי יהושע was strict even if
רוב rov. is כשרים. kshairim. So this follows, so this obviously is
not רבי יהושע. רבי יהושע is strict even by רוב כשרים. rov
kshairim. This will go by the רוב. rov. So when she doesn't
have an ability to claim, in that case we're just going to
look at the percentages. She doesn't know, let's look at the story
of רוב. rov Okay. So let's take a look.
Okay, we have one minute, let's read one more line. אמר ליה
רבא לרב נחמן. Amar lei Rava l'Rav Nachman. So רבא said to
רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, רבי יוחנן בן נורי דאמר כמאן? Rabbi Yochanan
ben Nuri d'amar k'man? Who's רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan ben
Nuri going by? אי כרבן גמליאל אפילו ברוב פסולים נמי מכשיר. Ei
k'Rabban Gamliel afilu b'rov psulim nami machshir. If it's like רבן גמליאל
that I just said, רבן גמליאל said even if most are פסולים,
psulim, of course there's an obvious difference. רבן גמליאל'ס Rabban Gamliel's case
was she said she knew who she slept with. Okay, אי כרבי
יהושע אפילו ברוב כשרים נמי פוסל. ei k'Rabbi Yehoshua afilu b'rov kshairim
nami posel. If it's by רבי יהושע, he would invalidate even by
רוב כשרים. rov kshairim. אמר ליה, he said to him, הכי אמר
רב יהודה אמר רב, hachi amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, בקרונות של
ציפורי היה מעשה, b'karonot shel Tzippori haya maaseh, וכדרב אמי. u'kh'Rav Ami.
Okay,
so now we, this is way too much to get into right
now, so we will find out the answer to this secret question
tomorrow. Although the easy answer is that רבן גמליאל'ס Rabban Gamliel's case
she says she knows who the guy
is and here she doesn't, we need to go by רוב. rov.
But we will find out tomorrow how the גמרא explains what are
the scenarios you need רוב and what are the scenarios you don't
need רוב.
Make sure that I put it all together. So then she's saying
whatever it is, רבן גמליאל says okay, we believe her, but then
it's not necessarily an...